{
  "reference_number": "8219",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Climate change is the biggest issue of our time. It has to be made a priority at the earliest opportunity."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I don't think I'm informed enough to answer this."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to the impacts of climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There needs to be clear directives and actions showing what will be done about climate change. Not just \"sometime in the future\" but\n right now plus plans in five years time, in ten years time etc. This problem is now. I am 23 years old. I'm going to have a partner, a\n\n family, a career, a life. This problem will affect my generation the most."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "I agree with the stance as stated on page 12 of the discussion document: \"there will be a long-term approach to climate change that\n endures political cycles\". I feel like the issue of climate change is too important to be way-layed by political and party lines and values.\n\n If the climate change commission could have some overarching sway and hold on the budgets and targets, this would work well and\n the government has to to take those into consideration before changing anything. Independence from specific party interference is\n crucial."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The bill should require the government to set out actions, be very transparent about when, why and how they will achieve them. This\nis an issue for New Zealand that requires clear action, not just a desire to do better. We actually have to set out when and how we will\n\ndo it and ACTUALLY go through with it. Having these set out plans will enable the public to keep the government to account. I agree\nwith the proposal that a brief annual report is produced to show how New Zealand is tracking towards the emissions budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "These aren't the most important things but I thought I would comment about the need to work with communication mediums/media\n\nfor national campaigns driving a societal push towards meeting these budgets, and the education sector to educate young people\nand the innovators of the future about net-zero initiatives and response to climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The CCC should advise the government plus the government should be required to respond to any recommendations made by the\nCCC with reasons for/against etc. They should be held accountable to the advice of the CCC even though they aren't BOUND by it.\n\nTherefore I agree with page 42 \"Advisory, with mechanisms built in to hold Government to account\"."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree. I am happy to see commitment to Maori on this list and \"community engagement and communication\" as I believe a part of\n\nthe commission needs to focus on actually engaging Kiwis with the issue of climate change and \"getting them on board\" as such."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to the impacts of climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am concerned about if we uptake electric vehicles - what will happen to the cars we already have - how will we dispose of them? I\n\nwould hope the bill outlines how we will transition to an 100% renewable transport model effectively. Also regarding the recycling\ncrisis arising from China - I hope this bill will set out actions for investing in onshore industries to manage our own waste. To be more\n\nsustainable, we have to invest in sustainable initiatives. Kaitiakitanga is very important to me as a born and bred kiwi. These values\nshould play a large part in our actions for net carbon zero by 2050. There is no second chance. We have to act NOW. I agree with the\n\npoints raised below the following on page 41 \"For the Climate Change Commission to be successful and become a trusted and\nstable part of New Zealandâ€™s government institutions, it would need.\" Finally, Is there going to be legislation that ensures foreign\n\ncorporations comply by these plans if they do business in NZ? E.g. film industry, international business events, foreign exporters to\nNZ, airlines etc.?\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
